欢迎收看本期《每日宇航员》,我是Tim Dodd
- Hi it's me, Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut.
SpaceX,美国太空探索技术公司,以下简称"太空叉"
我现在在太空叉位于德州博卡奇卡的全新发射场
I'm here at SpaceX's brand new launch facility in Boca Chica, Texas
来瞧瞧火箭发动机中的圣杯——太空叉即将到来的猛禽发动机
to check out the holy grail of rocket engines and that's SpaceX's upcoming Raptor engine.
像这样的发动机以前从未用在火箭上
An engine like this has never actually been used on a rocket before.
它是一款以甲烷为燃料的全流量分级燃烧循环发动机
Now this is a methane powered full flow staged combustion cycle engine.
说到火箭发动机,其复杂程度简直难得吓人
Talking about a rocket engine that this complex can be really intimidating.
为了将猛禽发动机与其他发动机、其他发动机循环方式进行对比
And in order to put it into context against other engines and other engine cycles
我们将从全方位角度把猛禽发动机和其他各种发动机进行比较
we're gonna do a full comparison of the Raptor engine versus a bunch of other engines
包括太空叉当前主力梅林发动机
including SpaceX's current workhorse the Merlin engine
对比航天飞机主发动机RS-25
against the RS-25, the Space Shuttle main engine.
Saturn V的F-1发动机
the F-1 engine that powered the Saturn 5.
RD-180发动机
The RD-180
和同样使用甲烷为燃料的蓝色起源的BE-4发动机
and Blue Origin's BE-4 that also runs on methane.
同时,除了全流量分级燃烧循环这一特性以外
And as if the full flow of staged combustion cycle wasn't enough,
太空叉还做出了独一无二的选择
SpaceX is also doing something else unique.
他们要使用液态甲烷作为燃料
They're powering that thing with liquid methane
这种燃料现实中从未用在入轨级火箭上
and that's something that's actually never been done on an orbital class rocket.
所以我们打算了解一下甲烷燃料的性质
So we're gonna take a look at the characteristics of methane
从而探寻太空叉选择甲烷而不是其他燃料的原因
and see if we can figure out why SpaceX chose methane instead of any other common propellant.
现在猛禽发动机其实在各方面都不是最好的
Now this engine isn't really the best at anything.
它推力不是最大
It's not the most powerful.
推重比不是最高
It's not the highest thrust to weight ratio of any engine.
效率甚至也不是最高
It's not even the most efficient
但它在很多方面非常突出
but it does a lot of things really really well.
所以希望看完本期视频后我们能知道为何猛禽发动机如此特别
So by the end of this video hopefully we have all the context understand why the Raptor engine is special
它和其他火箭(发动机)相比如何
how it compares to other rockets
为何它使用液态甲烷做燃料
why it's using liquid methane
也希望我们能了解,它到底是不是最强火箭发动机
and then hopefully we'll know if it really is the king of rocket engines.
走起吧~
Let's get started.
事先提醒一下刚点进视频的你们
- In case you didn't notice when you clicked on this video,
注意一下进度条长度
this is a very, very long video.
抱歉……抱歉个头啊
Sorry, not sorry,
但如果你真的像我一样
but if you're anything like me
听说了很多猛禽发动机的各种传闻
you keep hearing a lot of hype about the Raptor engine
你想深入了解它
and you want to appreciate it
但你又不知道从何查起
but you don't even know where to start.
Emm,我花了很长时间学习了一个这方面的内容
Well, I've spent quite a while really studying up on the subject
所以我有一个很好的基础
so I can lay down a good foundation
可以让你们真的非常极其完全彻底通透地了解猛禽发动机
in order to help us really truly fully appreciate the Raptor engine.
好吧,骗你们的,其实是全部的火箭发动机
Well, and quite frankly all rocket engines.
而如果你像我一样
And if you're anything like me
或许这些图表你是见得多了
maybe you've stared at diagrams like this or like this or like this one
多到看了几小时感觉脑子要爆炸了一样
for hours until you feel like your head's going to explode.
所以为了避免大家脑子爆炸
So in order to avoid that
我给大家精简出几个非常简单的版本
I've actually whipped up some really simple versions
供大家了解火箭发动机的多种循环方式
of rocket engine cycles for all of us to enjoy
希望大家能从中学到这些不明觉厉的概念
which will hopefully help us grasp these crazy concepts.
但如果你不是第一次当空降兵
But in case this isn't your first rodeo
那么指挥部提供坐标如下,欢迎大家空降
here's the timestamps if you want to jump to a certain section.
评论区也会放这些空降坐标
There's also links in the description to each section
还会有我的网站Everydayastronaut.com上本期视频的文字版的链接
as well as an article version of this entire video at my website, Everydayastronaut.com
供大家更深入地了解其中一些数据内容
in case you want to study some of the numbers a little more in depth
以及一些材料的出处
or see sources of some of the material.
开篇我们先快速讲一些物理学的内容
Now we're gonna start off with a super quick physics lesson
先别着急右上角
but bear with me.
我们要直接深入讲很多本质上的细节
We're gonna dive in and get plenty of nitty gritty details.
好,我们先从这开始
Okay. Let's start off with this.
火箭基本就是一个大燃料罐里面装着很多燃料
Rockets are basically just propellant with some skin around it to keep it in place
燃料罐的菊花有个东西能把燃料超快的喷射出去
and they have a thing on the back that can throw said propellant really, really fast
更简单的说,燃料喷射的速度越快越好
and to way oversimplify it even more, the faster you can throw that propellant the better.
想做到此事最简单的办法是以很高的压力在燃料罐中储存燃料
Now the easiest way to do this is by storing all the propellant in your tanks under really high pressure
然后在燃料罐一端放一个阀门
then put a valve on one end of the tank
再放一个喷嘴来让燃料加速从而产生推力
and a propelling nozzle that accelerates the propellant into workable thrust.
搞定
Done.
没有多么厉害的泵、也没有多么复杂的系统
No crazy pumps or complicated systems
开个阀门,喷就完事了
just open a valve and let her rip.
这种叫做挤压供应火箭发动机,有这么几种主要类型:
This is called a pressure fed rocket engine and there's a few main types:
冷气、单组元及双组元挤压供应式发动机
cold gas, monoprop and bipropellant pressure fed engines.
你会发现这些经常用在反作用控制系统上
You'll often find these used in reaction control systems
因为它们简单、可靠、反应迅速
because they're simple, reliable, and they react quickly.
但挤压供应发动机有一个巨大的限制因素
But pressure fed engines have one big limiting factor.
压力总是从高处流向低处
Pressure always flows from high to low
所以发动机的压强永远不能比燃料罐高
so the engine can never be higher pressure than the propellant tanks.
同时,为了保存高压燃料
In order to store propellant under high pressure,
你的燃料罐必须非常厚实
your tanks will need to be strong
非常、非常厚实
and therefore thicker, and thicker,
让你的重量也越来越大
and heavier, and heavier.
来看看复合材料压力容器,也叫COPV
Look at composite overwrapped pressure vessels or COPVs.
它们能够以超过10000PSI、700bar(70MPa)的压力储存气体
They're capable of storing gases at almost 10000 PSI or 700 bar.
即便如此,其可容纳燃料量与压强仍然有限
And despite this there's still a limited amount of propellant and pressure they can store.
当你想把载荷送进轨道的时候,这也不会提高很多运力
And this does not scale up very well when you're trying to deliver a payload to orbit.
所以聪明的火箭科学家们很快意识到
So smart rocket scientists quickly realized
想让火箭尽可能的轻
in order to make the rocket as lightweight as possible
那只能做一件事——提高焓
there's really only one thing they could do: increase the enthalpy.
这乐队名可太劲爆了
That would be a great metal band name.
多亏了因特网
You're welcome Internet.
焓主要是体积、压强、温度的关系
Enthalpy is basically the relationship between volume pressure and temperature.
燃烧室内更高的压强和温度等于更高的效率
A higher pressure and temperature inside the combustion chamber equals higher efficiency
而更多的质量从火箭喷出带来的是更高的推力
and more mass shoved through the rocket engine equals more thrust.
所以想要把更多燃料挤进发动机
So in order to shove more propellant into the engine
你可以提高燃料罐的压强
you could either increase the pressure in the tanks
或者简单地使用非常大功率的泵把燃料挤进燃烧室
or just shoot the propellant into the combustion chamber with a really high powered pump.
Emmmm,听起来第二个主意很不错
Emmmmm…The second option sounds like a pretty good idea.
但泵每秒会推动上百升燃料,需要很多……
But pumps moving hundreds of liters of fuel per second require a lot,
需要非常极其相当多的能量才能驱动
and boy do I mean, a lot of energy to power them.
所以假设我们有一个小火箭发动机
So what if you took a tiny rocket engine,
然后打算在右边放一个涡轮让泵转得飞快?
and aimed it right a turbine to spin it up really, really fast?
你可以把火箭燃料的一部分化学能转换成动能
You can exchange some of the rocket propellant's chemical energy for kinetic energy
从而驱动这些大功率的燃料泵
which could then be used to spin these powerful pumps.
欢迎来到涡轮泵与分级燃烧循环的课堂
Welcome to turbo pumps and the staged combustion cycle.
但你还会遇到一些限制因素
But you've still got some limiting factors here
比如高压总会流向低压时怎么办
like how high pressure always wants to go to low pressure
热量会融化周围东西的时候怎么办
and how heat has that habit of melting stuff.
所以你要把这些都放到检查单里
So you've got to keep all these things in check
才能再去尝试榨干你的发动机的每一滴性能
while trying to squeeze every bit of power out of your engine.
我们有很多种循环方式可以讲到
There's actually a lot of different variations of the cycles that we could talk about
但我打算只讲其中三种最常见的
but I'm going to stick with the three most common
或者说,在了解猛禽发动机之前需要知道的三种最重要的循环方式
or at least the three that matter the most when putting the Raptor into context.
我们要讲燃气发生器循环、部分流量分级燃烧循环
We have the gas generator cycle, the partial flow staged combustion cycle
最后我们讲全流量分级燃烧循环
and lastly we'll look at the full flow staged combustion cycle
或许在未来的视频中
and perhaps in a future video
我会尝试做所有液体火箭发动机的所有循环方式
I'll try and do a full rundown of all liquid fueled rocket engines
包括最新的一些方法,比如火箭实验室Electron火箭的电动泵
including fun new alternatives like the electric pump fed engine seen on Rocket Lab's Electron rocket.
我们先从燃气发生器循环开始,也叫开式循环
Let's start with the gas generator cycle known as the open cycle.
这可能是液体燃料火箭发动机里最常见的循环方式
This is probably one of the most common types of liquid fueled rocket engine used on orbital rockets.
它肯定比挤压供应系统复杂,但也还算简单
It's definitely more complicated than a pressure fed system but it's fairly simple,
至少和那些闭式循环的发动机相比
well at least compared to their closed cycle counterparts.
现在我要极度简化它,以方便大众百姓们理解
Now I'm gonna way, way oversimplify this so it's as easy to grasp as humanly possible.
在现实生活中,发动机上到处都有无数的阀门、线缆和细小的管路
In real life, there's literally dozens of valves, a hive of wires, and extra tiny little pipes everywhere,
有氦气为燃料罐增压
helium to back pressure the tanks
燃料会流经喷管、燃烧室来为其冷却
fuel flowing through the nozzle and the combustion chamber to cool it
预燃室、燃烧室内还要有点火源
and there is an ignition source for the preburner and the combustion chamber.
为了让其更加简化更易理解
But again for the purpose of making this as simple and as digestible as possible,
你们只要知道图中省略了很多东西就好
just know there's a lot of stuff missing from these diagrams.
但从现在开始我们要关注这些发动机内的流动情况
But for now we're going to focus on the flow of these engines
从而在一开始掌握这个概念
so we can grasp that concept first.
燃气发生器循环通过一个涡轮泵把燃料和氧化剂泵入燃烧室
The gas generator cycle works by pumping the fuel and oxidizer into the combustion chamber using a turbo pump.
涡轮泵有几个主要部件
The turbo pump has a few main parts
一个小型火箭发动机称为预燃室
a mini rocket engine called the preburner,
涡轮通过轴给一或两个燃料泵提供动力,从而把燃料泵入燃烧室
a turbine connected to a shaft and then a pump or two that push propellant into the combustion chamber.
"动力包"一般是老外的叫法
在中国通常叫做"半系统"
你或许听说过涡轮泵(和预燃室)组合叫做动力包
Now you might hear the turbo pump assembly called the power pack
因为它真的就是给发动机提供动力的东西
because it really is what powers the engine.
在开式循环中,预燃室中燃烧过的燃料会直接排出
In the open cycle system, the spent propellant from the preburner is simply dumped overboard
不提供任何显著的推力
and does not contribute any significant thrust.
这使得开式循环效率更低,因为驱动泵所使用的燃料和氧化剂基本全浪费了
This makes it less efficient since the fuel and oxidizer used to spin the pumps is basically wasted.
这里一个小插曲是,涡轮泵本身有一个先有鸡还是先有蛋的问题
Now the funny thing about a turbo pump is that it kind of has a chicken and egg syndrome situation
使其很难启动
that makes it pretty difficult to start up
因为驱动涡轮泵的预燃室需要高压燃料和氧化剂才能运行
since the preburner that powers the turbo pump needs high pressure fuel and oxidizer to operate.
所以预燃室需要涡轮泵转动才能让自己有完全可运行的压力状态
So the preburner requires the turbo pumps to spin before it can get up to full operational pressure itself
但涡轮泵又需要预燃室点火才能驱动自己
but the turbo pumps need the preburner to fire in order to spin the turbo pumps.
但预燃室又需要涡轮泵……好吧
But the preburner needs the turbo pumps to ... Yeah.
明白问题所在了吧
You can see where this is going.
这使得点燃燃气发生器循环发动机很需要技巧
This makes starting a gas generator pretty tricky.
有几种方法能够做到,但我不打算在本期视频中讲
There's a few ways to do this but we don't need to get into all that in this video.
听起来是个未来某期视频很不错的素材
That sounds like a fun topic for future videos though.
所以我们回到涡轮泵
So back to the turbo pumps.
记得压力总会从高处流向低处吧
Remember pressure always flows from high to low
所以涡轮泵压力要比燃烧室压力高
so the turbo pumps need to be a higher pressure than the chamber pressure.
这意味着进入预燃室的管道是整个火箭发动机里压力最高的地方
And this means the inlets leading to the preburner
is actually the highest pressure point in the entire rocket engine.
其余下游部分与之相比都是低压
Everything else downstream is lower pressure
但注意这个地方
but notice something here.
RP-1(Rocket Propellant 1),1号火箭燃料,以下简称煤油
来看看太空叉使用煤油和液氧作燃料的梅林发动机
Take a look at SpaceX's Merlin engine which runs on RP-1 or rocket propellant 1 and liquid oxygen.
注意预燃室废气管喷出的黑烟
Notice how black the smoke is coming out of the preburner exhaust.
为什么从那排出的尾气比火箭主燃烧室喷出的更黑呢?
Why would it be so sooty compared to the main combustion chamber
几乎都看不见火焰了
which leaves almost no visible exhaust?
这是因为火箭燃料(燃烧时)可达到上千摄氏度
Well that's because rocket propellant can get super hot like thousands and thousands of degrees Celsius.
为了保证温度不会高到让涡轮乃至整个涡轮泵组件熔化
So to make sure the temperature isn't so hot that it melts the turbine and the entire turbo pump assembly,
就要保证它的温度低到能够持续运转的程度
they need to make sure it's cool enough to continually operate.
以最佳燃料、氧化剂比例运转会有最高的效率,会产生最多的能量
Running at the perfect fuel and oxidizer ratio is the most efficient and releases the most energy
但也会产生极大的热量
but it also produces a crazy amount of heat.
所以为了保证温度够低
So in order to keep the temperatures low
你可以让预燃室内的燃烧比稍微低于最优比
you can run the preburner at a less than optimal ratio.
要么燃料过量,也叫富燃
So either too much fuel known as fuel rich
要么氧化剂过量,也叫富氧
or too much oxidizer or oxygen rich.
以富燃方式运行煤油发动机会有很多未燃烧的燃料以煤烟的形式冒出
Running an RP-1 engine fuel rich means you'll see some unburned fuel appearing as dark clouds of soot.
高压下不完全燃烧的碳原子会形成聚合物
the highly pressurized unburned carbon molecules bond and form polymers
这个过程称为结焦
which is a process known as coking.
煤烟会黏在所有其经过的表面
This soot starts to stick to everything it touches
可以堵塞喷注器甚至直接损伤涡轮本身
and can block injectors or even do damage to the turbine itself.
那如果你不想浪费所有高压燃料呢?
So what if you didn't want to waste all that highly pressurized propellant?
毕竟你为了降温都选择富燃了
I mean after all since it's running cooler by being fuel rich
那不就是有更多的未燃烧的燃料被浪费了吗?
doesn't that mean there's a bunch of unburned fuel literally being wasted?
能不能干脆把热的废气用管子怼回(主)燃烧室?
What if you could just pipe that hot exhaust gas and put it into the combustion chamber?
欢迎来到闭式循环的课堂
Welcome to the closed cycle.
闭式循环或者叫分级循环会提高发动机的效率
The closed cycle or staged combustion cycle increases engine efficiency
方法是使用原本会直接排出的废气
by using what would normally be lost exhausts
并将它和主燃烧室连接起来
and connects it to the combustion chamber
从而提升压力、提高效率
to help increase pressure and also increase efficiency.
所以我们把梅林发动机拿出来,把循环"关闭"起来
So let's take the Merlin engine and try closing the loop.
拿起排气管,直接怼进主燃烧室
Let's take the exhaust and just pipe it straight into the combustion chamber.
你可拉倒吧
Uh-oh, oh no!
我们让一大堆煤烟糊死了所有喷注器
We just put a bunch of soot and clogged all the injectors.
老铁你甭想上天了
You do not go to space today my friend.
但这有几种解决办法,我们看看苏联是怎么解决的
But there's a few solutions to this problem so let's see how the Soviets solved it.
校注:这里老外犯了个错,世界第一型闭式循环发动机应该是
科罗廖夫设计局研制的S1.5400液氧煤油发动机,(GRAU代码为11D33)
1960年就随闪电号运载火箭完成了首飞
而NK-15的首飞时间是1969年
他们造的第一个能用的闭式循环发动机是N-1登月火箭的NK-15发动机
The first operational closed cycle engine they made was the NK-15 design for their N-1 moon rocket.
它们之后升级成了NK-33
They later upgraded it to the NK-33
校注:严格来说RD-180和NK-15/33是不同设计局的产品
系统结构布局差别很大,不能简单地认为是衍生关系
随后衍生出很多种型号,包括RD-180
and then many versions from there stemmed out including the RD-180
至今仍在Atlas V火箭上使用
which is what is used on the Atlas V today.
NK-15和NK-33和梅林发动机一样都是以煤油为燃料
Since the NK-15 and NK-33 runs on RP-1 like the Merlin
但又不能让预燃室富燃运行,因为会遇到结焦的问题
you can't run your preburners fuel rich because of the coking problem.
所以如果你想造一种以煤油为燃料的闭式循环发动机
So if you want to create a closed cycle engine with RP-1,
办法就是让预燃室富氧运行
the answer is running the preburner oxygen rich.
很简单不是吗
Easy as that, right?
那你就是把超热高压的气态氧灌了进去
Well now you're blasting superheated highly pressurized gaseous oxygen
那你几乎会把精密的、低容错的涡轮叶片吹成一锅粥
which will turn just about anything into soup right at your precision machine crazy low tolerance turbine blade.
美国认为这样做是不可能的
Doing so is actually considered impossible by the United States,
他们基本上是放弃尝试了
and they basically gave up on trying.
他们认为不存在某种合金可以承受如此恶劣的条件
They didn't think a metal alloy existed that could withstand these crazy crazy conditions,
他们也不相信苏联
and they didn't believe the Soviets
会造出如此高效、大推力的煤油发动机
had made such an efficient and powerful RP-1-powered engine
直到苏联解体以后
until after the collapse of the Soviet Union
美国工程师才见到了那些发动机,并对其进行第一手测试
and the US engineers got to see them and test them out firsthand.
但苏联当年真的很努力
But the Soviets had indeed worked their butts off,
他们的确利用科学的魔法造出了特种合金
and they had made a special alloy that can magically with science
可以承受预燃室内富氧的恶劣条件
withstand the crazy conditions of an oxygen rich preburner.
在闭式循环发动机中,你不是使用一部分燃料和一部分氧化剂
With a closed cycle engine, you don't just use some fuel and some oxidizer
让它们在预燃室内燃烧并驱动涡轮
and burn that in the preburner to spin the turbine.
而是把所有的氧化剂或者燃料以过量的形式通过涡轮
You actually shoot all of the rich propellant through the turbine.
所以对于富氧循环来说
So with an oxygen rich cycle
所有氧气都会经过预燃室
all of the oxygen actually goes through the preburner
然后把特定量的燃料输往预燃室
and just the right amount of fuel goes to the preburner.
你只需要给涡轮刚好足够的燃料来驱动燃料泵
You only need enough to give the turbine the right amount of energy to spin the pumps fast enough
从而给预燃室和主燃烧室提供正确的压力
to get the right pressures for the preburner and the combustion chamber
以此产生正确的功率,把火箭送进太空
to make the right amount of power to shoot the thing into space.
牛逼吧
Just crazy.
回到富氧预燃室
So back to this oxygen rich preburner.
热的气态氧全部进入主燃烧室,遇到了液体燃料
That now hot gaseous oxygen is forced into the combustion chamber where it meets liquid fuel.
结合后发生爆炸,得到了一个完整高效的燃烧过程
They meet and go boom and we get a nice clean and efficient burn
不浪费一滴燃料
without really wasting any propellant.
但和所有发动机一样,燃烧室压力不能高于泵压力
But still like all engines the chamber pressure can not be higher than the pump pressure
所以燃料泵弱小无助的外表却承受着巨大的负担
so the pumps actually have a lot of weight on their tiny little metal shoulders.
所以如果你以为美国就那样坐视不管
Now if you're sitting there thinking that the United States just sat back
让苏联人拿走所有闭式循环的荣耀,那你就错了
and let the Soviets have all the closed cycle glory, you'd be wrong.
美国的确多花了点时间,但他们最终还是造出来了闭式循环发动机
It took the United States a little bit longer but they eventually figured out a closed cycle engine.
但它和富氧循环非常不同
But it was very different from the oxygen rich cycle.
美国研发的闭式循环发动机的预燃室是富燃的
The United States pursued a closed loop cycle but they went with a fuel rich preburner.
等下,刚不是说富燃预燃室的废气有过多的煤烟
But wait, we just learned that fuel rich preburners' exhaust is so sooty
会毁掉一切东西吗?
that it pretty much ruins anything, right?
呃……如果你使用的是煤油等高碳含量燃料的话的确
Well sure if you're using RP-1 or any other carbon heavy fuel
煤烟结焦是必然结果
that's definitely going to be the outcome.
所以美国用了另一种不同的燃料:氢
So the United States went with a different fuel: hydrogen.
OK,我们现在避免了让高温高压气态氧冲击那些宝贝机器
Okay, so now we've avoided the problem of blasting crazy hot high pressure oxygen at anything dear and precious
但我们又遇到新麻烦了
but now we've opened up a new can of worms.
液氢的密度远远小于煤油和液氧
Hydrogen is significantly less dense than RP-1 or liquid oxygen.
液氢密度如此地小
It's so much less dense,
以至于需要非常巨大、复杂的燃料泵才能准确地将氢送往燃烧室
it takes a huge and really complex turbo pump to flow the right amount of hydrogen into the combustion chamber.
而煤油和液氧的密度接近、混合比接近
Since RP-1 and LOX are relatively similar in density and in the ratios
让它们可以用一根轴、同一个预燃室
they can be run on a single shaft using a single preburner.
因此Rocketdyne的工程师研发了RS-25发动机
Because of this the engineers at Rocketdyne pursued an engine known as the RS-25
将在当时用在航天飞机上
which would go on to power the Space Shuttle.
他们意识到(氢和氧的)两个泵区别非常大
They realized that because of the large difference between the pumps
可能需要两个不同的预燃室
they might as well have two different preburners,
一个驱动氢泵一个驱动氧泵
one for the hydrogen pump and one for the oxygen pump.
他们的确这样做了
So that's what they did.
但使用两根独立的轴又带来了新问题
But having two separate shafts created another new problem.
工程师把高温高压的氢气
Now engineers were putting high pressure hot gaseous hydrogen
就放在了同一根连杆驱动的液氧泵的隔壁
on the same shaft right next door to the liquid oxygen pump.
一旦那一部分氢气从预燃室泄漏(到液氧泵)
If some of that hydrogen would leak out of the preburner
就会在液氧泵内引发大爆炸,结果会很惨
it would start a fire in the LOX pump which is catastrophically bad.
氢又非常难储存,因为它密度太低,太轻了
Hydrogen is also very hard to contain because it's so not dense, un-dense, lightweight
它会从细小缝隙中泄漏出去,到处乱飘
it likes to sneak through cracks and get out anywhere it can.
所以工程师们不得不设计一个复杂的密封装置放置氢泄漏
So engineers had to make an elaborate seal to keep the hot hydrogen from sneaking out.
这种密封方法叫吹气密封
The seal required for this is called a purge seal
实际中是用氦气加压的,使其成为压力最高的地方
and it's actually pressurized by helium so that it's the highest point of pressure.
即使密封泄漏,流出来的也是惰性的氦气
So if the seal leaks it just leaks inert helium.
很精巧的方法,但要注意
It's genius but take a look at
液氧泵和氢泵的密封部分的不同
how different the LOX turbo pump and the hydrogen turbo pump seals look.
可以看出工程师们为了防止氢泄漏花了多少时间精力
You can tell how much more engineering time and effort had to go into the hydrogen seals.
想出这些设计的人简直是疯子
I mean the people that think of this stuff are nuts.
RS-25发动机几乎仍然是人类制造过的最好的发动机
The RS-25 is still considered to be about the best engine ever made
有着较高的推重比和与之不符的高效率
with a fairly high thrust to weight ratio and unmatched efficiency.
OK现在我们讲完了双预燃室富燃的RS-25发动机
Okay now that we've talked all about the dual preburner fuel rich RS-25,
接下来看其简化的图表
here's a simplified diagram of that.
我没费劲地把两个泵画成不一样的大小
Now I didn't bother making the fuel pumps different sizes
我只想让大家关注流向,让其变得尽可能简单
and I just want to focus on the flow here and help make that as simple as possible.
但请记住,RS-25发动机以富燃方式运转的两个预燃室
But do note both preburners of the RS-25 run fuel rich
虽然看起来一样,但驱动的是不同的两个泵
so although they might look the same they power different pumps
我会把动画再在这放几秒,让你们多理解一下
and I'll just let this run here for a few seconds so you can study it for a bit
也不要担心,我还会在讲完所有循环种类后把所有的图放一起
but don't worry we'll also put all these up on screen at the same time once we cover them all.
闭式循环提升了发动机的整体性能,有很大的优势
So the closed cycle improves the overall performance of the engine and is highly advantageous.
那还能有哪些改进呢?
So how can it get any better than this?
Full Flow Staged Combustion Cycle,"全流量分级燃烧循环",以下简称FFSCC
我们终于可以开始讲全流量分级燃烧循环了
We're finally ready to talk about the full flow staged combustion cycle
基本上是组合了刚讲过的上述两种循环方式
which basically just combines the two cycle methods we just talked about.
在FFSCC中
With the full flow staged combustion cycle,
你会用两个预燃室,一个富燃运行,一个富氧运行
you take two preburners one that runs fuel rich and one that runs oxygen rich.
富燃预燃室驱动燃料泵,富氧预燃室驱动液氧泵
The fuel rich preburner powers the fuel pump and the oxygen rich preburner powers the LOX pump.
这意味着FFSCC需要克服富氧情况下的困难
This means the full flow staged combustion cycle needs to tackle the oxygen rich problems
前文已提过,需要研发出特种合金来克服
which again is solved by developing very strong metal alloys.
所以太空叉在自家工厂研发出了名为"SX500"的特种合金
So SpaceX developed their own super alloys in house that they named SX500.
根据马一龙所述,SX500可以承受800bar(80MPa)的高温富氧燃气
According to Elon Musk it's capable of over 800 bar of hot oxygen rich gas.
这算是研发猛禽发动机过程中的最大障碍之一了
That may have been one of the biggest hurdles in developing the Raptor engine.
幸运的是,富燃的预燃室只驱动燃料泵
Luckily the fuel rich side only pumps fuel
所以如果高温(富燃)燃气从泵轴处泄漏
so if some of that hot fuel leaks through the seal on the shaft
它也只会遇到更多的燃料,没啥大事
it just comes in contact with more fuel which is kind of no big deal.
所以不需要那些非常非常精细的密封装置
So no need for one of those really really elaborate seals.
FFSCC不太可能用煤油作燃料,因为富燃预燃室会有结焦的问题
Full flow likely wouldn't work with RP-1 due to the coking problems with a fuel rich preburner
而其他燃料仍可以使用这种设计
but other fuels are still valid to use this design.
但这个稍后再说
But more on that in a minute.
该系统的优势在于
The advantage of the system is that
燃料和氧化剂在到达主燃烧室的时候都是气态
since both the fuel and the oxidizer arrive in the combustion chamber as a hot gas
它们会更加充分的燃烧,可以达到更高的温度
there's better combustion and hotter temperatures can be achieved.
又没有我们之前提到过的种种极端限制
There's also less of a need for that crazy ceiling system as we mentioned earlier
这对于仅几次或者不翻新就能多次重复使用的发动机来说肯定是很有利的
and that's definitely a good thing when you plan to reuse your engine over and over
with little to no refurbishment between flights.
最后,因为其本身流量的提高
And lastly because there's an inherent increase in mass flow
或者说燃料会更快地射入预燃室
or how quickly all the propellant is shooting into the preburner
涡轮可以以更低的温度、更低的压力工作
the turbines can run cooler and at lower pressures
因为驱动涡轮泵所需的燃料氧化剂混合比大大减小
because the ratio of fuel and oxidizer needed to spin the turbo pumps is much lower.
而你们这样想
And think of it this way
在开式循环的预燃室中你只想用尽可能少的燃料和氧化剂,因为它们都浪费了
in an open cycle you only want to use as little fuel and oxidizer as possible
in the preburner since it's all wasted
而你又想让它越热越好,因为那样才更有效率
and you want it to be as hot as withstandable to make it more efficient
但在全流量循环中,所有的燃料和所有的氧化剂都会经过预燃室
but with the full flow cycle all of the fuel and all of the oxidizer goes through the preburners
所以驱动涡轮泵需要多少燃料氧化剂你就可以烧多少
so you can burn just exactly as much propellant as necessary to power the turbo pumps.
而更(凉)爽的是你两边的预燃室会极度富燃与极度富氧
But the cool thing is your fuel to oxidizer ratios will be so crazy fuel rich and crazy oxygen rich
使得两边涡轮的温度大大降低
that the temperatures at the turbines will be much lower
意味着可以大大提升涡轮泵组件的寿命
and this means longer lifespans for the turbo pump assembly.
这还意味着在主燃烧室内的燃烧更多,预燃室内的燃烧更少
It also means more combustion happens in the combustion chamber and less in the preburner.
现在到了牛逼的部分了
Now here's the crazy part.
FFSCC迄今为止只有三个例子
Only three engines have demonstrated the full flow staged combustion cycle, ever.
六十年代苏联研发了从未上过天的RD-270发动机
In the 60s the Soviets developed an engine called the RD-270 which never flew
在21世纪初,Aerojet和Rocketdyne研发过一款集成动力验证器
and in the early 2000s Aerojet and Rocketdyne worked on an integrated powerhead demonstrator called
注意,是"集成动力验证器"
wait for it, the Integrated Powerhead Demonstrator,
最后连试车台都没撑过去
which again never made it past the test stand.
第三次FFSCC发动机的尝试就是太空叉的猛禽发动机了
And the third attempt to developing a full flow staged combustion cycle engine is SpaceX's Raptor engine.
当当当当,没错
Ta-da, that's right.
猛禽发动机是这种疯狂类型发动机的"唯三"之一
The Raptor engine is only the third attempt at making this crazy type of engine.
也是唯一一个把发动机试车台留下的发动机
It's the first to ever do any type of work and leave a test stand
希望老天保佑,让它成为第一个入轨的FFSCC发动机吧
and fingers crossed, it'll be the first full flow staged combustion cycle engine to reach orbit.
好吧,几乎任何和这个发动机有关的内容都是零的突破
Well actually just about anything this engine does will be a first.
这意味着太空叉需要克服重重艰难险阻
This means SpaceX had to tackle some crazy crazy problems.
我的意思不单单指富燃循环所遇到的困难
I mean not only that same problem that plagues oxidizer rich cycles
比如需要有超超级强的合金
like having to have a really really strong metal alloy.
他们还要学会如何控制两个不同的预燃室和两个不同的循环
They also had to learn how to control two different preburners and two different cycles
从而产生比之前所有主燃烧室都要高的压力
to create the highest pressures of any chamber pressure ever.
他们刚刚打破了RD-180的265bar(26.5MPa)的压力记录
They just beat the RD-180's record of about 265 bar
达到了270bar(27MPa),而他们还觉得不够
when they hit 270 bar and they're not even done.
他们希望的是主燃烧室达到300bar(30MPa)的压力
They're hoping for 300 bar inside the combustion chamber.
简直牛逼疯了,这点我们稍后还会讲
That's nuts and we'll talk more about that in a second
但在继续之前,我们既然已经讲完了所有要讲的发动机循环种类
but before we move on now that we've done a rundown on all these engines cycle types
我们把它们放到一起
let's put them all up on screen
播放一会,让大家能同时看到并挨个作出对比
and let them run for a bit so you can watch each one and compare them side by side.
我知道对于我自己来说同屏看到这些动画是很有帮助的
I know for myself it helps a lot to see them all together on the same screen at the same time.
之前说过猛禽发动机不能使用煤油燃料运行富燃预燃室
Since the Raptor engine can't run a fuel rich preburner using RP-1,
你可能会想那最合乎逻辑的燃料就当属氢了
you'd think the next most logical choice would be hydrogen.
可太空叉既没有选择煤油也没选择液氢
Well SpaceX didn't opt for either RP-1 or hydrogen.
他们选择了液态甲烷
They went with liquid methane.
终于来到下一个话题了
So now we finally have another topic to touch on.
为什么太空叉选择液态甲烷作为猛禽发动机的燃料?
Why did SpaceX choose liquid methane for the Raptor engine?
甲烷有哪些优于液氢或煤油的特性?
What are the qualities that make it advantageous over hydrogen or RP-1?
迄今为止还没有液态甲烷发动机进入轨道
Today no liquid methane or otherwise known as methylox engine has gone to orbit.
所以它有哪些优点值得作为燃料呢?
So what qualities does it have that make it desirable?
我们把甲烷和煤油、氢作下对比
Let's take a look at methane compared to RP-1 and hydrogen.
我们把甲烷放在煤油和氢的中间
Let's put methane in between RP-1 and hydrogen.
你会很快知道原因
You'll see why here really quickly.
我们先看设计火箭一级时可能是最重要的因素
So let's start off with perhaps the biggest factor when designing your first stage,
燃料的密度
the density of the propellant.
燃料密度大,意味着同样质量的燃料,燃料罐可以更小更轻
Having a denser fuel means that tanks are smaller and lighter for a given mass of fuel.
更小的燃料罐等于更轻的火箭
A smaller tank equals a lighter rocket.
所以这是三种燃料的密度,单位是克每升
So here's the density of these three fuels measured in grams per liter.
就是说一升这样的燃料有多重,准确讲是质量是多少
In other words how much does one liter of this stuff weigh or really what's its mass.
先是煤油,密度是每升813克
Starting off with RP-1, one liter is around 813 grams.
煤油的密度是液氢的10倍,后者只有70克每升
RP-1 is 11 times more dense than hydrogen which is only 70 grams per liter
而液态甲烷密度刚好在中间,422克每升
and methylox is right in the middle at 422 grams per liter.
记得飞艇曾经是用氢气填充让其比空气轻吗?
Remember how airships or zeppelins used to be filled with hydrogen to make them lighter than air?
嗯,这是因为氢气密度比我们大气还要低
Well, that's because hydrogen is so much less dense in our atmosphere
虽然易燃,但它还是填充气球的最好选择
it makes for an excellent albeit really flammable gas for a balloon.
我们都听过兴登堡的事故吧?
I mean we all remember the Hindenburg, right?
还要注意的是煤油的813克每升是一个平均值
It should also be noted that 813 grams per liter is an average for RP-1
太空叉会为Falcon 9和Falcon Heavy的煤油降温从而提升2-4%的密度
but SpaceX chills their RP-1 in their Falcon 9 and Falcon Heavy for about a 2 to 4% increase in density.
但历史上煤油的密度差不多就是813克每升
But historically RP-1's density is right around that 813 grams per liter.
所以从密度来讲,甲烷的性能在煤油和液氢的正中间
So in the case of density methane is kind of right in the middle of the two others
但除了密度还有很多因素
but there's more to it than just density.
我们还要考虑燃料燃烧量与氧化剂燃烧量的比值
We also need to take into consideration the ratio of how much fuel is burned
compared to how much oxidizer is burned.
这就是氧化剂燃料混合比
This is the oxidizer to fuel ratio.
这里事情就有趣起来了,表格也会小有改变
So here's where things get a little more interesting and the tables turn just a little bit.
火箭工程师们要计算的是燃料的质量
Rocket engineers have to take into account the mass of the fuel
以及相应的燃料罐的重量
and the corresponding weight of the tanks
所以他们不会让燃料处在完全理想的燃烧比
so they don't actually burn propellant at the perfect stoichiometric combustion ratio.
他们找到了一个合适的折中来平衡燃料罐体积、推力和比冲
They find the perfect happy medium that balances tank size with thrust output and specific impulse.
我们来看看工程师要遇到的燃料氧化剂质量比
Let's look at the mass ratios for fuel and oxidizer that the engineers have come up with.
对于煤油,燃烧1克煤油需要消耗2.7克氧
So for these numbers RP-1 is burned at 2.7 grams of oxygen to 1 gram of RP-1.
燃烧1克氢需要6克氧
Hydrogen burns at 6 grams of oxygen to 1 gram of hydrogen
燃烧1克甲烷需要3.7克氧
and methane burns at 3.7 grams of oxygen to 1 gram of methane.
这些数字可以稍稍减小之前密度的巨大差异
These numbers can now help offset a little the massive difference in density.
我们把这些可视化来方便大家理解
So let's visualize this to help make it easier to digest.
液氧是1141克每升
Liquid oxygen is 1141 grams per liter.
比煤油大一点
It's a little more dense than RP-1.
而以2.7:1的质量燃烧液氧和煤油
So burning LOX and RP-1 at a 2.7 to 1 ratio
那么每升液氧你需要0.5升多一点的煤油
for every liter of LOX you'd need a little over half a liter of RP-1.
接下来说氢
Next up let's do hydrogen.
煤油密度是液氢的11倍
Now with hydrogen being 11 times less dense than RP-1
你或许以为两者燃料罐要差11倍
you'd think it'd need a tank that's 11 times bigger.
但幸运的是工程师们发现了液氧和液氢6:1的折中的质量比
But luckily engineers have found that it pays to burn LOX and hydrogen at a 6 to 1 ratio for a good compromise.
这意味着每升液氧只需要2.7升的液氢
This means for each liter of LOX you'd need 2.7 liters of hydrogen
那么你的液氢罐大概要有煤油罐的五倍大
so your fuel tank needs to be approximately five times larger compared to RP-1.
还是有用的
So yeah that helps.
这也是为什么我们看到液氢燃料的Delta IV和煤油燃料的Falcon 9时
That's why when we look at a hydrogen powered Delta IV versus an RP-1 powered Falcon 9
你可以注意到Falcon 9的燃料罐比液氧罐小
you can see the fuel tank is much smaller than the LOX tank on the Falcon 9
但这在Delta IV上则是反过来
but the Delta IV is about the opposite.
液氧罐比燃料罐小得多
The LOX tank is much smaller than its fuel tank.
接下来我们看看甲烷,这就有意思了
So now let's take a look at methane. And this one gets kind of interesting.
液氧密度是甲烷的2.7倍
LOX is 2.7 times more dense than liquid methane
但燃烧1克甲烷消耗3.7克液氧
but the burn ratio is 3.7 grams of oxygen to one gram of methane.
所以每升液氧需要0.73升的甲烷
So you need 0.73 liters of methane for every liter of LOX.
换句话说,你的燃料罐需要
In other words your fuel tank would need to be
比煤油罐大大约40%
about 40% bigger for methylox than it would need to be for RP-1
尽管煤油的密度是甲烷的几乎两倍
despite RP-1 actually being almost twice as dense
而对比液氢,后者的燃料罐将是甲烷的3.7倍大
and compared to hydrogen its fuel tank would be about 3.7 times smaller.
所以燃料氧化剂比让甲烷罐的体积比液氢罐更接近煤油罐的体积
So the fuel to oxidizer ratio helps make a methane fuel tank a lot closer to an RP-1 tank
than it is to a hydrogen tank.
另一个所有火箭发动机都有的重要因素是效率
Another huge variable with any rocket engine is how efficient it is.
衡量标准是"比冲"(Isp)
This is measured in specific impulse or Isp
你可以认为它有点像汽车的燃油经济性
but you can think of it kind of like a fuel economy of a gas powered car.
比冲高类似于汽车每升燃油能跑得更远
So a high specific impulse would be similar to a high mile per gallon or kilometer per liter.
理解比冲的最好办法是想象你有燃料和氧化剂共1千克
The best way to think of specific impulse is to imagine you had one kilogram of propellant
你的发动机能以9.8牛顿的力推进多少秒
for how many seconds can the engine push with 9.8 newtons of force.
发动机能以那样大的力、那种质量的燃料推进越久
The longer it can sip on that fuel while still pushing that hard
它的比冲就越高,也就能用同样多的燃料做更多的事
the higher its specific impulse and therefore the more work it can do with the same amount of fuel.
所以的确有点像燃油经济性
So again kind of like its fuel economy.
所以比冲越高,干同样的事情燃料消耗就越少
So the higher the specific impulse the less fuel it takes to do the same amount of work
这是好的
which is a good thing.
燃料效率高的发动机非常重要
A fuel efficient engine is extremely important
而现在由于每种燃料的分子组成、燃烧释放能量不同
and now due to the molecular way of each fuel and their energy released when burned
它们将废气以多快从喷嘴喷出的潜力也不同
there's a different potential for how quickly the exhaust gas can be expelled out the nozzle.
这意味着每种燃料都有不同的理论比冲
This means each fuel has a different theoretical specific impulse.
在理想、完美的世界中,煤油发动机比冲可以达到370秒
In ideal and perfect world an RP-1 powered engine could achieve about 370 seconds.
液氢燃料发动机可以达到532秒
An ideal hydrogen powered engine could get 532 seconds
你猜怎么着?
and guess what?
甲烷发动机又在中间,459秒
A methane powered engine is right in the middle with 459 seconds.
现实中的例子会低一些
Real world examples of this are much lower
像真空型梅林1D发动机这样的煤油发动机比冲大约在350秒
with RP-1 engine seeing around 350 seconds like the Merlin 1D Vacuum
像真空型猛禽发动机这样的甲烷发动机比冲未来或许可以达到380秒
run 380 seconds for a methane powered engine like the Raptor vacuum might be someday
而像RL-10B-2发动机这样的液氢发动机比冲大约在465秒左右
and about 465 seconds for a hydrogen powered engine like the RL-10B-2.
接下来说说每种燃料的燃烧温度
Next, let's talk about how hot each fuel burns.
燃烧温度更低,对发动机更好,可以潜在地提升发动机寿命
A fuel that burns cooler is easier on the engine and potentially makes for a longer lifespan.
煤油燃烧温度3670开,液氢是3070开
RP-1 can burn up to 3670 Kelvin, hydrogen 3070 Kelvin,
你猜怎么着?甲烷又在中间,温度是3550开
and if you haven't guessed it by now, methane is again between the two at 3550 Kelvin.
既然说到了温度,咱们再说说这些燃料的沸点
Speaking of thermal considerations let's look at the boiling point for each of these fuels
也就是液体燃料会在什么温度时变为气体
or at what point does the liquid fuel boil off and turn into a gas.
因为所有燃料都必须保持液态才能维持其密度
Since all of these fuels need to remain in their liquid state in order to stay dense
沸点越高保存就越简单
the higher the temperature the easier it is to store the fuel.
更高的沸点也意味着燃料罐需要很少甚至不需要隔热措施防止燃料沸腾
A higher boiling point also means less or even no insulation on the tanks
to keep the propellant from boiling off.
而减少隔热措施就意味着燃料罐更轻,液!
And of course less insulation means lighter tanks, YEAH!
煤油的沸点高达490开,比水还要高
RP-1 has a very high boiling point even higher than water at 490 Kelvin.
而另一边的液氢则接近绝对零度,只有贼冷贼冷的20开
Hydrogen on the other hand is near absolute zero at a crazy cold 20 Kelvin.
这种低温使其需要非常严肃地考虑保温隔热措施
That's insanely cold and it takes serious consideration to keep anything at that temperature
而甲烷又在中间,沸点是111开
and like the Goldilocks it is methane is between the two at 111 Kelvin
虽然还是非常低,仍然需要有温度上的考虑
which although that's still very cold and requires thermal considerations
但至少其沸点和液氧很接近,所以还凑合
it at least boils off at a temperature similar to LOX, so there is that
而正因为其沸点和液氧很接近
and because it's so close to the temperature of LOX
燃料罐和液氧罐可以使用共底储箱,继续减轻火箭重量
the tanks can share a common dome which makes the vehicle lighter.
而液氧和液氢的温度差距如此大
LOX and hydrogen's temperatures very so wildly
以至于液氧会让液氢沸腾,液氢会让液氧凝固
that LOX will boil off hydrogen and the hydrogen will freeze LOX solid.
然后说排出的废气
Now, on to the exhausts.
这些发动机燃烧产生的两种产物是什么?
What are the byproducts of combustion with these engines?
煤油是唯一一种会产生不完全燃烧碳并排放进大气中的
RP-1 is really the only one of these three that really pollutes with
any unburned carbons being left in our atmosphere
同时还会产生水蒸气
alongside with some water vapor
而液氢只产生水蒸气
but hydrogen only produces water vapor
甲烷的产物也是水蒸气,外加一些二氧化碳
and methane produces some carbon dioxide and water vapor as well.
但有趣的是,信不信由你,对于温室气体来说
But an interesting note now believe it or not as far as greenhouse gases go,
高空大气中的水可能很糟糕
water in the upper atmosphere can be pretty bad
我以后会做一期视频讲到火箭的污染
but I'll be doing a video in the future all about how much rockets pollute
讲讲它们带来的空气污染、海洋污染,甚至还会讲到太空垃圾
talking about their air pollution, also their ocean pollution and even space debris is a consideration.
所以敬请期待吧,我觉得会是一期很有意思的视频
So stand by because I think that video is going to be awesome.
还有一个我们稍后会快速略过但很多人会讨论的问题是燃料的价格
Now one metric that we're just kind of going to gloss over really quick but talk about it generally is the cost.
这些往往差异很大,实际上也很难知道某种燃料的确切价格
And these tend to vary considerably and it's actually really hard to pin down the exact prices reliably.
而火箭用的煤油本身就是高度精炼后的航空燃油
So for the considerations RP-1 is basically just a highly refined jet fuel
而航空燃油则是高度精炼后的煤油,煤油是高度精炼后的柴油
which jet fuel is a highly refined kerosene which kerosene is a highly refined diesel.
所以完全可以认为火箭煤油比柴油贵得多
So it's safe to assume it's going to be more expensive than diesel.
氢虽然含量很多但也非常贵
Hydrogen is also relatively expensive despite being abundant.
无论是提纯、保存还是运输都很困难
Refining it storing it and transporting it can be hard
而另一方面甲烷则是天然气的主要成分,相对便宜
but methane on the other hand is basically the same thing as natural gas and can be relatively cheap.
而如果你成吨买燃料的话,燃料的总价格差距就会进一步拉大
Now when you're talking about buying literally tons of fuel the fuel costs can add up quickly
所以虽然燃料的价格通常不是很重要的因素
so although the cost of fuel shouldn't factor in too much
但它也是不容忽视的
it certainly is a consideration
但没有实锤的数据摆着,我不愿意把它摆在我们的表格上
but without hard data on this one I don't even want to put it on our chart.
那么我们聊聊另一个有关燃料的话题,就是其生产方式
So instead let's talk about the more important aspect of the fuel that's manufacturing it.
而这恰恰说明了太空叉把甲烷看成其未来很重要甚至必不可少的一环的原因
And here's where we get into specifically why SpaceX sees methane as an important
or even a necessary part of the company's future.
太空叉的终极目标是研发一个能多次运输人类往返火星的系统
SpaceX's ultimate goals are to develop a system capable of taking humans out to Mars and back over and over.
火星大气富含二氧化碳
The Martian atmosphere is CO2 rich.
而将其与火星表面或地下水结合后
Now combine that with water mining from the surface and subsurface water on Mars
利用电解、萨巴蒂尔反应
through electrolysis and the Sabatier process
火星大气就能制取甲烷燃料
the Martian atmosphere can be made into methane fuel
所以你不需要带所有供你返回的燃料
so you don't have to take all the fuel you need to get home with you.
你可以在火星就地取材
You can make it right there using Mars's resources.
这个过程叫原位资源利用(ISRU)
This is called in situ resource utilization or ISRU.
你现在可能在想
Now you might be thinking,
既然有水,为啥不能在火星表面制氢作位燃料呢
"Well, if there is water can't you just make hydrogen on the surface of Mars for your fuel?"
这倒没错,但液氢在长期任务中最大的问题之一
Well, yes but one of the biggest problems with hydrogen in long duration missions
就是液氢的沸点
is the boiling point of hydrogen.
别忘了,把氢保持在液态是非常费劲的事情
Remember, it takes serious considerations to maintain hydrogen in a liquid state
而这又是用氢作为燃料的必要步骤
and that's necessary to be useful as a fuel
所以对于太空叉来说,甲烷更合适
so for SpaceX methane makes a lot of sense.
密度相对较高,火箭尺寸可以更合理
It's fairly dense meaning the rocket sizes are pretty reasonable.
效率相对较高,燃烧充分,适用于高度可复用发动机
It's fairly efficient, it burns clean and it makes for a highly reusable engine.
燃烧温度相对较低
It burns relatively cool
有助于延长发动机寿命,有助于其复用
helping expand the lifespan of an engine which again is good for reusability.
甲烷很便宜,也很容易生产
It's cheap and easy to produce
可以在火星表面很容易制取
and can be easily reproduced on the surface of Mars.
OK,液
Okay. Yeah.
我们终于讲到这了
We finally made it this far.
现在大家已经掌握了不同发动机循环的原理
and now that we have a strong grasp of how different engine cycles operate
以及它们各自使用的燃料
and the fuels they use
我们终于可以把它们放在一起,对比一下各自的参数
we can finally line them all up side by side and compare their metrics
以便于我们了解各种发动机定位如何了
to help us appreciate where each engine sits.
现在我们把它们按照燃料种类和循环方式排列好
So now we're going to lineup each engine by their fuel type and their cycles.
先从太空叉用于Falcon 9和Falcon Heavy火箭上的开式循环梅林发动机开始
So let's start off with SpaceX's open cycle Merlin engine that powers their Falcon 9 and Falcon Heavy rockets.
然后是用于Atlas V火箭的动力机械科研生产联合体富氧闭式循环RD-180发动机
NPO Energomash's oxygen rich closed cycle RD-180 that we see power the Atlas V rocket
然后是Rocketdyne生产的用于Saturn V的开式循环F-1发动机
and Rocketdyne's open cycle F-1 that powers a Saturn V
上述三种发动机都使用煤油为燃料
which all three of these engines run on RP-1.
接下来是太空叉的FFSCC猛禽发动机
Then we have SpaceX's full flow staged combustion cycle Raptor engine
将用于Starship和其超重型的助推上
that will power the Starship and Super Heavy booster
然后是蓝色起源的闭式循环富氧甲烷BE-4发动机
and then we have Blue Origin's closed cycle oxygen rich methane powered BE-4 engine
将用于其新格伦火箭和联合发射联盟即将到来的火神火箭上
that will power their New Glenn rocket and ULA's upcoming Vulcan rocket
然后是Aerojet和Rocketdyne用于航天飞机上的闭式循环富燃RS-25发动机
and then we have Aerojet Rocketdyne's closed cycle fuel rich RS-25 engine that powered the Space Shuttle
将用于即将到来的以液氢为燃料的SLS火箭
and will power the upcoming SLS rocket which runs on hydrogen.
先补充一句
A few quick notes here.
猛禽发动机和BE-4发动机在视频制作时仍处于研发状态
The Raptor and the BE-4 as of the making of this video are still in development
所以我们所拥有的数据要么是其当前进展状态
so the numbers we have here are either their current state of progress
比如猛禽发动机,数据几乎每天都在变
like the Raptor which is constantly improving literally every day
再比如BE-4,是蓝色起源目前仍未达标的发动机
and in the case of the BE-4, those are the target goals for the engine which Blue Origin has yet to hit.
所以要知道这些数据未来肯定会有改变
So just keep that in mind that these numbers are definitely subject to change
也正因如此,不要忘了
and now because of this don't forget to
查看视频说明内附的文字版链接
check in with the article version attached in the description of this video.
视频中的数字未来很可能会过时
This video will likely date itself with some of these numbers
我又不能更新这个视频内容,但我可以更新我自己网站的内容
and I can't update this video but I can update the website when more info comes through.
所以如果大家打算使用这些数据作为参考
So if you're looking to use any of these numbers as a source
请一定务必确保前往我的网站以获取更新
please, please, please double check the website for any updates.
另一个要说的是有关RD-180发动机的
Another fun note quick is look at the RD-180.
不要被迷惑,这是一台发动机
Now don't be confused. This is a single engine
只不过有两个燃烧室
it just has two combustion chambers.
它只有一个涡轮泵
There's only a single turbo pump
并把能量分开给了两个燃烧室
that splits its power into two combustion chambers.
苏联解决了高温氧气富氧闭式循环的顶级难题
The Soviet Union was able to solve the crazy hot oxygen rich closed cycle problem
却没解决大型发动机燃烧稳定性的问题
but they were unable to solve combustion instability of large engines.
所以他们没用使用单个大燃烧室,而是使用了多个小的
So instead of one large combustion chamber they made multiple small ones.
那么首先我们看看这些发动机的海平面推力
So first up let's take a look at their total thrust output at sea level.
因为它们全都是从海平面开始工作的,所以这样比较还算公平
Since all these engines run at sea level that's probably a fair place to compare them.
咱们从最小的开始,这样比较有意思
Let's go from the least amount of thrust to the most for fun.
梅林发动机推力是0.84兆牛
The Merlin produces 0.84 meganewtons of thrust.
RS-25发动机推力是1.86兆牛
The RS-25 produces 1.86 meganewtons.
猛禽发动机推力目前是2兆牛
The Raptor currently is at 2 meganewtons.
BE-4发动机推力预期可达2.4兆牛
The BE-4 is hoping to hit 2.4 meganewtons.
RD-180发动机推力是3.83兆牛
The RD-180 3.83 meganewtons
F-1发动机至今仍然是推力冠军,高达6.77兆牛
and the F-1 is still the king out of these at 6.77 meganewtons.
曾有一款发动机叫RD-170
Now there was an engine called the RD-170
推力其实比F-1发动机还要大
which actually produced more thrust than the F-1
但它飞行次数极少,且与表格里这些发动机关系不大
but since it barely flew I figured it wasn't as relevant in this lineup.
我觉得选一些使用次数比较多的发动机作为例子更好
I thought it'd probably a good idea to go with engines that have actually been used a lot.
推力是个好东西,但或许重要性只和
Thrust is great but what's maybe just as important
设计火箭时的推重比一样重要
when designing rocket is the thrust to weight ratio
或者说是发动机重量与其产生推力相比如何
or how heavy the engine is compared to how much thrust it produces.
高推重比的发动机
A higher thrust to weight ratio engine
最终会让火箭拖着更少的死重飞行
ultimately means less dead weight the rocket needs to lug around.
我们从推重比最小的开始说起
Let's start from the lowest to highest here.
推重比最小的是航天飞机的RS-25发动机,73:1
The lowest is actually the Space Shuttles RS-25 at 73 to 1.
然后是RD-180发动机,78:1
Then there is the RD-180 which is 78 to 1.
然后是BE-4发动机,大约80:1
Then we have the BE-4 at around 80 to 1
别忘了这个数字并不是完全精确的
but keep in mind we don't actually have a really good number on this.
所以应该还有浮动空间
So there might be some wiggle room there.
然后是F-1发动机,94:1
Then the F-1 is 94 to 1,
接下来是猛禽发动机,目前推重比是107:1
then we have the Raptor which is at about 107 to 1 for now.
最后梅林发动机摘得桂冠,推重比达到惊人的198:1
And lastly the Merlin is actually the leader here with an astonishing 198 to 1 thrust to weight ratio.
这发动机太带劲了
Yeah, that thing is a powerhouse.
OK,推力的确是好事
Okay. Thrust is great and all
但如果效率低下的话推力再大有啥用
but who cares how powerful an engine is if it's terribly inefficient.
所以接下来我们对比它们的比冲,仍然是以秒为单位
So next up let's check out their specific impulse which again is measured in seconds.
比冲最低的是F-1发动机,只有263-304秒
So starting with the least efficient engine which is the F-1 engine at 263 to 304 seconds
然后是梅林发动机,比冲是282-311秒
then the Merlin engine at 282 to 311 seconds.
然后是RD-180发动机,比冲是311-338秒
Then we get the RD-180 at 311 seconds to 338 seconds
同一梯队的BE-4发动机比冲大约是310-340秒
and somewhere in that same ballpark is the BE-4 which is around 310 to 340 seconds.
然后是猛禽发动机,比冲大约是330-350秒
Next up is the Raptor engine which is 330 seconds to around 350 seconds,
最后比冲最高的是遥遥领先的RS-25发动机,为366-452秒
and lastly the king here by far is the RS-25 which is 366 to 452 seconds.
哇
Wow.
而同时影响推力和比冲的因素是(燃烧室)室压
Now one of the factors that affect both the thrust and specific impulse is chamber pressure.
大体上讲就是室压越高推力越大
Now generally the higher the chamber pressure the more thrust
而发动机潜在的效率也就越大
and potentially more efficient the engine can be
而推力相同的情况下,更高的室压可以让发动机更小
so higher chamber pressures let an engine be smaller for a given thrust level
同样可以提高其推重比
also improving their thrust to weight ratio.
这当中室压最小的发动机是F-1,只有70bar(7MPa)
The baby here is actually the F-1 which only had 70 bar in this chamber pressure.
但我现在要提醒你们一句
Now, I do need to pause here for a second and remind you
即使是70bar(7MPa),也相当于70倍大气压强
that 70 bar is still 70 times the atmospheric pressure
相当于你在水下700米受到的压力
or the same amount of pressure you'd experience at 700 meters underwater.
惊了
Yikes.
所以即使是这当中最低的室压,也是惊人的大
Okay so even the lowest chamber pressure is still mind-bogglingly high.
接下来是梅林发动机的97bar(9.7MPa),BE-4是大约135bar(13.5MPa)
So next up is the Merlin engine at 97 bar then the BE-4 will be around 135-ish bar
然后是RS-25发动机206bar(20.6MPa)
then the RS-25 which is 206 bar
然后是现役发动机中室压最高的RD-180发动机,约257bar(25.7MPa)
then the RD-180 which has been considered the king of operational engines at about 257 bar
它是目前表格中仅次于猛禽发动机的
that is until the Raptor engine which is now kind of online
而后者将是新的室压王者
which is considered the new king of chamber pressure
目前可达到270bar(27MPa),并有希望达到300bar(30MPa)
at 270 bars currently and they hope to get that thing up to 300 bar.
而300bar(30MPa)将会是海底三千米的压力
Again, 300 bar is like being three kilometers deep in the ocean.
简直难以想象
I can't even fathom.
好了,发动机本身的参数说得差不多了
Okay, that's enough of the specs of these engines.
我们来看看它们使用时要考虑的事项,首先是预计造价
Now, let's look at their operational considerations starting with their approximate cost.
需要重申的是这仍然是很难确定的一个数值
Now again this can be kind of hard to nail down,
所以表格中将是最低的估计值
so these are the best estimates that I could come up with.
这些数字全都考虑到通货膨胀而换算成了今天的美元
These numbers do factor in inflation to make them all in today's dollars though.
我打算从最贵的讲到最便宜的
Let's go with the most expensive, and work our way down to the least expensive engine.
表格中最贵的是RS-25发动机
The most expensive engine in the lineup is the RS-25
每台发动机标价超过5000万美元
which has a sticker price of over $50 million per engine.
惊了²
Yikes.
接下来是F-1发动机,每台大约三千万美元
Then we have the F-1 which was about $30 million per engine
然后是RD-180发动机,每台2500万美元
then the RD-180 which is $25 million per engine
然后是BE-4发动机,每台大约800万美元
then the BE-4 which is around $8 million per engine.
关于猛禽发动机,马一龙曾提到
and for the Raptor Elan has mentioned
他认为猛禽发动机的造价可以和梅林发动机一样低
he thinks he can produce the Raptor for cheaper than or close to the Merlin engine
前提是他们能够降低当前发动机大量的复杂度
if they can remove a lot of the complexity that the current engine has.
所以我觉得200万美元算是个不错的估计值
So for now we're gonna say $2 million is a pretty decent ballpark.
然后是梅林发动机,我觉得造价可以低于100万美元
Then we have the Merlin engine which is less than a million I think.
OK,造价是一方面
Okay, well cost is one thing
但另一个有关造价的非常重要的考量是发动机是否可复用
but another strong consideration for the cost of the engine is whether or not it's reusable.
而这里面只有RD-180和F-1发动机是不可复用的
And here only the RD-180 and the F-1 were not reusable
或者至少从未复用过
or at least never reused
这和其余所有(将)会多次复用的发动机是不同的
which is different than all these other engines which will all be reused multiple times.
RS-25发动机复用记录是单台发动机复用19次
The RS-25 was reused over and over with the record being 19 flights out of a single engine.
当然了,每次中间都要经历几个月的翻新
Well then again that's after a few months of refurbishment.
梅林发动机预期可以做到不进行大规模翻新而飞行多达10次
The Merlin is hoping to see up to 10 flights without major refurbishment.
我们了解到BE-4发动机设计可复用次数可达25次
We know a design goal for the BE-4 is to be reused up to 25 times.
而我认为猛禽发动机预期可飞行50次,但理想是美好的
And I think the Raptor engine hopes to see up to 50 flights but again aspirations are one thing.
现实如何就另说了
We'll see how history tweets its claims.
但这里还有件有趣的事情是
But one quick fun little story here is
不要忘记太空叉现在在Falcon 9和Falcon Heavy火箭上使用的梅林发动机
don't forget the Merlin engine which SpaceX currently uses on the Falcon 9 and Falcon Heavy rockets
在每次上发射台之前都已经点火过很多次了
are already fired a bunch of times before they even make it to the pad.
每台发动机在加州霍桑制造,送到德州麦克格雷戈试车台
Each engine that is built goes from Hawthorne, California to their test stand at McGregor, Texas,
在那里进行全程点火
where it does a full duration burn
然后送回加州
then those engines go back to California
安装到一级火箭底部的一圈八个中间一个的结构上
where they're integrated onto the Octaweb which is at the base of the vehicle.
然后整个一级火箭会再次送到麦克格雷戈进行全程点火
Then they take the entire stage and they take it back out to McGregor for a full duration static fire.
所以发动机相当于又经历了一整次任务飞行
So it goes through the whole mission basically again.
然后运到发射台,进行一次很短的静态点火
Then they ship it to the launch pad where does a short static fire
最后才进行任务
and then it flies the mission.
所以发动机在首次上天的时候,就已经经历过三次任务时长的运行了
So it's already done like three missions in duration of firing
by the time it flies for the first time
所以我真的不完全确定一台发动机能进行最多多少次全程点火
so I'm not entirely sure what the most times a single engine has done a full duration burn.
我们知道有些一级还曾在试车台上
We know that some of the cores were set out on the pad
点火了很长很长很长时间,反反复复很多次
and fired for a really really really long time multiple times over and over
所以我认为他们可能用一台发动机进行过几乎10次全程点火
so I think they've probably done almost 10 flight full duration burns out of a single engine.
但当然我肯定相信他们能说到做到
But you know I have no doubt they can probably do that if they say.
因为在发动机不经过翻新复用方面,没有任何比太空叉更有经验
I mean they have more experience in this than anybody already reusing engines without really refurbishing them.
所以我就信了他们的话吧
So I'm gonna definitely take their word for it.
有关价格方面,这些数字还有一些更有趣的内容
On the topic of price there's actually some things here
that start to get really interesting when we start looking at these numbers.
首先是马一龙在2019年2月的推特中提过的参数
The first is an interesting metric that Elan talked about once in a tweet in February of 2019
他说他们希望让猛禽优势体现在"推价比"上
saying they hope to make the Raptor get better at their thrust to dollar ratio.
你一细想会发现这个概念很有意思
Now this is a really interesting concept when you think about it.
如果推力相同时一个大发动机比两个小的更便宜或者更贵,那谁还会在意价格
Who cares how much an engine costs
if one big engine is cheaper than two smaller ones for the same thrust or vice versa.
所以接下来我们看看这些发动机的"推价比"(美元/千牛推力)
So let's actually take a look at the dollar to kilonewton ratio of these engines.
先从推价比最高的开始
Starting with the most expensive dollar to kilonewton engine
RS-25发动机推价比高达26881美元/千牛推力
which is the RS-25 at a crazy $26,881 to kilonewton of thrust
然后是RD-180发动机的6527美元/千牛推力
then the RD-180 which is $6527 to one kilonewton
然后是F-1发动机的4431美元/千牛推力
followed by the F-1 at $4431 per kilonewton
然后是BE-4发动机的3333美元/千牛推力
and then we get to the BE-4 which is $3333 to one kilonewton,
然后是梅林发动机的1170美元/千牛推力
the Merlin engine at $1170 per kilonewton
然后是猛禽发动机,大约是1000美元/千牛推力
and the Raptor at around $1000 per kilonewton
但我们还可以再进一步想
but now we can go even another step further
我们已经知道了它们的推价比,但我们还知道各自的复用潜力
since we know their dollar to kilonewton ratio but we also know their reusability potential.
所以我们可以预测它们潜在的单次推价比[美元/(千牛推力×次)]
Now we can predict their potential costs per kilonewton per flight
数据基于其各自实际可复用次数
which changes based on how reusable these engines actually are.
首先RD-180和F-1发动机无法复用
For start the RD-180 and the F-1 aren't reusable.
所以单次推价比等于推价比
Their price stays the same
但对于剩下的发动机,如果我们考虑进它们(将)飞行的次数
but for the rest of the engines, if we take into account how many flights they have/will have
我们就能看出RS-25发动机的复用抵消了之前的高推价比
now we start to see the RS-25 reusability pay off
它的单次推价比可以拉低到1414美元/(千牛推力×次)
and kind of close the gap bringing its potential cost down to just $1414 per kilonewton per flight.
但接下来更厉害
But here's where things get crazy.
蓝色起源的BE-4发动机可谓改变了游戏规则
Blue Origin's BE-4 has potential to truly be game changing
25次飞行的情况下单次推价比约133美元/(千牛推力×次)
at around $133 per kilonewton over 25 flights
与之相近的是梅林发动机的117美元/(千牛推力×次)
which could make it about as cheap to operate as the Merlin at $117 per kilonewton per flight.
但如果猛禽发动机兑现了它的承诺
But if the Raptor engine truly lives up to its hype
那它能把这个数值一路拉低至20美元/(千牛推力×次)
it could bring this number all the way down to $20 dollars per kilonewton per flight.
这才是彻底改变游戏规则
Now that is absolutely game changing.
诚然,造价和复用性是21世纪航天的焦点
Sure, money and reuseability is a 21st focus for spaceflight
但之前老生常谈的可靠性又如何呢?
but whatever happened to good old proven reliability?
首先我们看看这些发动机都飞了多少次
For this let's first look at how many operational flights each engine has had.
在制作本期视频的时候,猛禽和BE-4发动机都没有任何飞行次数
Now at the moment of shooting this video the Raptor and BE-4 haven't seen any operational flights
虽然猛禽发动机已经要离开试车台
although the Raptor is starting to leave the test stand
准备装到像Starhopper这样的测试载具上了
and is being used on test vehicles like the Starhopper.
但截至目前,它们都没有实际飞行记录
But for now, neither engine has a real flight record.
所以我们来看看其他发动机
So let's look at the other engines.
首先F-1发动机飞行了17次
First we have the F-1 engine which was used on 17 flights.
然后是梅林发动机的71次
Next up is the Merlin engine which is at 71 flights
很快就要超过RD-180发动机的79次了
and catching up quickly to the RD-180 which is at 79 flights
而它们中最多的是RS-25发动机的135次
but the king out of these was the RS-25 which saw 135 flights.
最后,它们在工作时的可靠性如何呢?
Now lastly, how about reliability in service?
参考飞行次数和这个数值后
Between the number of flights and this number
我们才能更好的了解发动机到底有多可靠
we can get a pretty good sense of how truly reliable an engine is.
而这个数值又很难确定
This number is really hard to just pin down
因为有些发动机可能过早关机
since some of the engines may have shut down early
但某几次的任务仍然成功了
but the mission was still a success on a few of these.
所以希望大家持保留意见
So take a few of these with a grain of salt.
BE-4和猛禽发动机数据仍然没有,因为都没上过天
Again the BE-4 and Raptor engine haven't flown yet. So those numbers are unavailable.
然后是航天飞机主发动机RS-25,可靠性超过99.5%
Then we have the Space Shuttle main engine which is over 99.5% reliable
在1985年7月29日STS-51-F任务上升中,航天飞机中央的RS-25发动机异常关机
也是整个航天飞机任务中唯一的一次飞行中主发动机失效
但对于发动机异常关机来说是很难定义的
but that gets hard to define when an engine doesn't fully shut down.
然后梅林发动机可靠性99.9%
And then we have the Merlin at 99.9% reliable.
每次发射要用10台发动机的情况下这还是很让人安慰的数值
It sure helps when you have 10 engines on each flight of the vehicle
而梅林发动机整个生涯也只有一次失效
and with only one engine ever failing early on in its career,
且那次任务仍然成功了
and despite that that mission was still a success.
所以梅林发动机是很可靠的
So, the Merlin is a very reliable engine.
而最后,理论上讲RD-180和F-1发动机是100%可靠的
Now to end this technically the RD-180 and the F-1 are 100% reliable
而F-1发动机也从未在飞行中异常关机过,我要在表格中为它的"100%"加粗
but with the F-1 never having shut down at all in any flight, it gets the bold here.
而根据每个人心中的成功与可靠性的定义
And depending on how you define success and reliability
理论上RD-180只能"算是"100%可靠
technically the RD-180 is only kind of 100% reliable
因为它运气超好
because it got really lucky ones.
在2016年Atlas V某次任务中它提前6秒关机
One time it shut down six seconds early on an Atlas V mission in 2016.
原因是一个阀门的故障,但任务仍然是成功的
This was due to a faulty valve but the mission went on to be a success
完全是运气好,因为半人马上面级为任务带了足够多的额外速度增量
because of some pure luck with the Centaur upper stage having enough spare Delta V to carry out the mission.
如果那个阀门再早一秒失效,那次任务就凉凉了
Had that valve failed even a second earlier that mission would have failed.
见识到那么多数据和考量点
Seeing all these numbers and considerations,
你可能会发现造一个火箭竟然要考虑这么多东西
it makes you realize just how many variables go into designing a rocket.
任何一个微小的改动
Change any one little thing
都能为整个设计带来巨大的连锁反应
and it can have this massive ripple effect on the entire design
从而影响到整个火箭的制造
and the implementation of the vehicle as a whole.
我们最后来回顾一下
So let's go back over all of this.
我们已经了解了所有循环方法、燃料种类,也知道了太空叉的愿景
Now that we know all the cycles, the fuels, the aspirations of SpaceX to see
那我们能不能想通为何会出现猛禽发动机
if we can figure out why the Raptor engine exists
并且能不能理解研发它的意义
and figure out if it's worth all the effort.
我们看看太空叉的终极计划
Let's look at SpaceX's ultimate plan.
制造一款可多次、完全可复用的火箭
Make a rapidly and fully reusable vehicle
让人类尽可能廉价地定期往返月球和火星
capable of sending humans to the Moon and Mars as inexpensively and routinely as possible.
和日常的火箭目标不太一样是吧
Not exactly your everyday goal for a rocket, huh?
为了能多次、完全可复用,发动机必须无结焦
In order to be rapidly and fully reusable the engine needs to run clean
且需要简单的涡轮泵密封以达到低维护,还需要低预燃室温度
and require low maintenance with simple turbo pump seals and low preburner temperatures.
Emmmm……
Emmmm…
甲烷燃料FFSCC发动机听上去不错×1
A methane fueled full flow staged combustion cycle engine sounds like a good fit.
为了可靠性、冗余性,和制造上的考虑
For reliability, redundancy, and scale of manufacturing considerations
配备多台发动机是个合理选择
it makes sense to employ a lot of engines.
为了让发动机尽可能小,推力尽可能大
In order to scale an engine down but maintain a high output
燃烧室室压就要高
chamber pressure needs to be high.
Emmmm……
Emmmm…
甲烷燃料FFSCC发动机听上去不错×2
Sounds like a methane fueled full flow staged combustion cycle engine is a good fit.
而对于行星际旅行来说,甲烷也更合理
For interplanetary trips methane makes the most sense
因为其沸点可以让去火星这种长期飞行变为可能
because its boiling point makes it usable on long duration trips to Mars
而且你猜怎么着?
which guess what?
你可以在火星上制取甲烷
You can produce methane on Mars.
所以对于行星际旅行,甲烷燃料FFSCC发动机听上去不错×3
So for interplanetary trips a methane fueled full flow staged combustion cycle engine sounds like a good fit.
甲烷密度还算大,燃料罐体积可以说得过去
Methane is fairly dense meaning the tank size remains reasonable.
这同样有利于行星际旅行,可以减少很多死重
Which again is good for interplanetary trips not needing to lug around a lot of dead weight
所以甲烷燃料FFSCC发动机听上去不错×4
making a methane fueled full flow staged combustion cycle a pretty good fit.
OK,我们最后总结一下
Okay so let's bring this all back around now.
猛禽发动机是最强火箭发动机吗?
Is the Raptor engine really the king of rocket engines?
好吧,火箭科学和所有东西一样都是一堆复杂东西的妥协罢了
Well rocket science like all things is a complex series of compromises.
它是最有效率的发动机吗?不是
Is it the most efficient engine? No.
它是推力最大的发动机吗?不是
Is it the most powerful engine? No.
它是最便宜的发动机吗?可能不是
Is it the cheapest engine? Probably not.
它是可复用性最强的发动机吗?或许吧
Is it the most reusable engine? Maybe.
它满足它的各项需求吗?
But does it do everything really well?
太满足了,它简直是为各项需求量身打造的
Yeah it is truly a Goldilocks engine doing everything it needs to do very very well.
完美适合你的行星际飞船
It is the perfect fit for your interplanetary spaceship
而且尽管它很复杂,但太空叉仍在飞快改进这款发动机
and despite its complexity SpaceX is developing this engine at a rapid pace.
你要是知道过去十年太空叉把梅林发动机改成啥样了就会明白
I mean knowing how much tweaking SpaceX did to their Merlin engine over a decade,
我们现在看到的梅林发动机还是太年轻
we're just at the infancy of the Raptor engine.
它只会变得越来越牛逼,这才是最可怕的
It's only gonna get better from here on out, which is crazy.
所以总的来讲,对于这样的需求来说,猛禽发动机的确是最好的
So all in all the Raptor engine is the king of this application.
它能实现太空叉Starship火箭的美好目标
It's a fantastic engine to fulfill SpaceX's goals for their Starship vehicle.
对于其他需求来说,它是最好的吗?
Would it be the king of other applications?
那就说不好了
Maybe, maybe not.
也正是它才让火箭科学家、工程师们每天都在做出那些疯狂决定
And only that decision for the rocket scientists and engineers
who get to make all those crazy decisions every single day.
所以你怎样想?
So what do you think?
费尽周折造这么一个疯狂的发动机值吗?
Is it worth all this hassle to develop such a crazy and complex engine?
这会是猛禽发动机的开始吗?
Is this just the beginning for the Raptor engine?
更重要的是,你觉得猛禽发动机是最强火箭发动机吗?
And most importantly, is the Raptor engine really the king of rocket engines?
欢迎在评论区留言
Let me know your thoughts in the comments below.
OK我知道本期视频里只有我这大脑袋叭叭地讲
Okay I know I say this every video,
但实际上没有粉丝Patreon上的赞助就不可能有这期视频
but I honestly could not have done this video without the help of my Patreon supporters.
他们不但在过去五个月内支持我做这期视频
They not only kept me sane for the past five months as I worked on this video
还帮我查找上面那些数据
but they also went over all the data with me.
他们给我这期视频制作上的反馈、建议
They give me great feedback and suggestions in the edits of this video.
如果你也想支持我所做的
If you want to help support what I do
或者为视频提供反馈,或者帮助撰写脚本、查找资料
or provide feedback in videos or help scripting research
或者你单纯想聊聊和太空有关的东西
or if you just want to hang out and talk space
那么请了解一下我们的独家Discord频道和Reddit子版块
consider joining our exclusive Discord channel and our exclusive subreddit
方法是前往Patreon.com/everydayastronaut成为赞助者
by becoming a Patreon member by going to Patreon.com/everydayastronaut.
感谢各位
Thank you guys.
真的,没有你们就没有这期视频
Seriously, I couldn't have made this video without you.
网上冲浪的同时顺便看看我的网店
And while you're online, be sure and check out my web store.
里面超多好东西,比如印着F-1发动机的T恤等等
Seriously, I have really cool things like these F-1 T-shirts, tons of other shirts.
经常会上新货,所以记得常来看看
There's lots of new merchandise popping up in there all the time so check back often.
我们有像格栅舵杯垫
We have things like grid fin not-a-coasters
帽子、衬衫、杯子、海报
and hats and shirts and mugs and prints,
五花八门的火箭周边
just literally tons of cool rocket stuff.
所以如果是你的菜
So if that's your type of thing,
请务必来everydayastronaut.com/shop这里逛逛
be sure and check out my web store everydayastronaut.com/shop
还可以去音乐标签下听听本期视频使用的音乐
and then click on the music tab if you want to check out any of the songs used in this video.
都是我过去几年写的曲子
It's all music that I've written over the years
苹果、iTunes、Spotify、谷歌音乐上都有
Apple, iTunes and Spotify and Google Music, all that stuff,
YouTube上还有这些音乐的视频版播放列表
and also there's a playlist right here on YouTube for music video versions of it too as well,
看看听听也很不错
which is a fun way to watch and listen.
记得推荐给朋友
So show it to a friend.
感谢大家
Thanks everybody.
今天就到这了,我是《每日宇航员》的Tim Dodd
That's gonna do it for me. I'm Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut
把太空知识带入寻常百姓家
bringing space down to earth for everyday people.